Finding Aid for the Anton Grot Papers LSC.0956
UCLA Library Special Collections
Anton Grot papers
1920-1950, undated
UCLA Library Special Collections
Grot, Anton, 1884-1974
LSC.0956
12.8 Linear Feet (13 boxes, 7 oversize boxes, 1 map folder)
Antocz Franciszek Groszewski (1884-1974) was born in Kelbasice, Poland and came to the U.S., 1909. His film career began in 1913 when he was hired by the Lubin Company to paint and design sets. He relocated to Los Angeles in 1922. He worked on a variety of films and was nominated for 5 Academy Awards. The collection consists of materials related to Grot's career as a motion picture set designer and art director. Includes original sketches in pencil, charcoal, and water color as well as photographs of completed sets and sketches.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Louise Marvin, 1967.
Gift of Mrs. Anton Grot, 1975, 1981.
Gift of Mrs. Florentine Gutowski, 1981.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9914706823606533
Biography
Antocz Franciszek Groszewski was born in Kelbasice, Poland, January 18, 1884; attended the Technical College in Königsberg, Germany majoring in interior decoration, illustration, and design; came to the U.S., 1909; started his film career in 1913 when he was hired by the Lubin Company to paint and design sets; moved to Los Angeles in 1922; head of the Warner Brothers Studio Art Department (1927); worked on a variety of films such as The Private Lives of Elizabeth and Essex (1938), Captain Blood (1935), The Sea Hawk (1940), and Mildred Pierce (1945); was nominated for 5 Academy Awards and in 1941 received a special Scientific/Technical Oscar for his invention of a water ripple and wave illusion machine first utilized in The Sea Hawk; retired 1948; died March 21, 1974.
Biographical Narrative
Anton Grot, motion picture art director, was head of the Art Department at Warner Brothers Studios from 1927-1948. Born in Kelbasice, Poland, and educated in Germany, Grot emigrated to the United States in 1909. He began his career in motion picture design when he was hired by the Lubin Company to paint and design sets. After working with directors such as Cecil B. DeMille and William K. Howard, Grot began his long association with Warner Brothers in 1927. He worked on a variety of films, including historical epics such as The Private Lives of Elizabeth and Essex (1938), contemporary dramas such as Mildred Pierce (1945) and romantic adventure films, most notably Captain Blood (1935) and The Sea Hawk (1940).
Lilace Hatayama, January 1979
Scope and Content
Collection consists of materials related to Grot's career as a motion picture set designer and art director. Includes original sketches in pencil, charcoal, and water color as well as photographs of completed sets and sketches.
Items Removed from Collection
Thames Television. The Art of Hollywood. Fifty years of art direction. A Thames Television exhibition at the Victoria and Albert Museum. London: Thames Televsion [1979] [132 p.] Gift of Brooke Whiting.
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Anton Grot Papers (1 item).
Sketches.; Motion picture art directors -- United States -- Archives.; Motion pictures -- Setting and scenery -- Archives.; Photographs.; Drawings.; Grot, Anton, 1884-1974 -- Archives
- Alias the Doctor
  - Alias the Doctor. Warner Brothers, 1932.; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alias the Doctor. Warner Brothers, 1932.; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Anthony Adverse
  - Anthony Adverse. Warner Brothers, 1936.; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anthony Adverse. Warner Brothers, 1936.; 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anthony Adverse. Warner Brothers, 1925, undated (Box 20, Folder 1-3, Folder 21)
    Scope and Contents
    4 drawings
- Blue Danube
  - Blue Danube. Pathe, 1928.; 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Body and Soul
  - Body and Soul., 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Broadway Gondolier
  - Broadway Gondolier. Warner Brothers, 1935.; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Broadway Gondolier. Warner Brothers, 1935.; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Cairo
  - Cairo., 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Captain Blood
  - Captain Blood. Warner Brothers, 1935.; 4 items. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Captain Blood. Warner Brothers, 1935.; 5 items. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Captain Blood. Warner Brothers, 1935.; 4 items. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Captain Blood. Warner Brothers, 1935.; 4 items. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Captain Blood. Warner Brothers, 1935.; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Captain Blood. Warner Brothers, 1935.; 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Captain Blood. Warner Brothers, 1935.; 4 items. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Captain Blood. Warner Brothers, 1935.; 4 items. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Country Doctor
  - Country Doctor. Producers Distributing Corporation, 1927.; 2 items. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Danton
  - Danton. Capitol Film Exchange, 1931.; 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Dispatch from Reuter
  - Dispatch from Reuter. Warner Brothers, 1940.; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    General note
    SEE ALSO: Box 16.
- Doctor X
  - Doctor X. Warner Brothers, 1932.; 3 items. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Don Q, Son of Zorro
  - Don Q, Son of Zorro. United Artists, 1925.; 1 item. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- For Lovers Only
  - For Lovers Only., 3 items. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - For Lovers Only., 3 items. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Godless Girl
  - Godless Girl. Pathe, 1929.; 2 items. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- The Great Garrick
  - The Great Garrick. Warner Brothers, 1937.; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Heartbreak
  - Heartbreak., 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Her Man
  - Her Man. Pathe, 1918.; 1 item. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Inspiration
  - Inspiration., 5 items. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Juarez
  - Juarez. Warner Brothers, 1939.; 4 items. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Juarez. Warner Brothers, 1939.; 4 items. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Juarez. Warner Brothers, 1939.; 3 items. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Juarez. Warner Brothers, 1939.; 4 items. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Juarez. Warner Brothers, 1939.; 4 items. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Juarez. Warner Brothers, 1939.; 5 items. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Juarez. Warner Brothers, 1939.; 4 items. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Juarez. Warner Brothers, 1939.; 4 items. (Box 2, Folder 15)
- King of Kings
  - King of Kings. Pathe, 1927.; 2 items. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- The King's Vacation
  - The King's Vacation. Warner Brothers, 1933.; 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- The Life of Emile Zola, also known as Truth is on the March
  - The Life of Emile Zola. Warner Brothers, 1937.; 4 items. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - The Life of Emile Zola. Warner Brothers, 1937.; 3 items. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - The Life of Emile Zola. Warner Brothers, 1937.; 3 items. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The Life of Emile Zola. Warner Brothers, 1937.; 4 items. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - The Life of Emile Zola. Warner Brothers, 1937.; 3 items. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The Life of Emile Zola. Warner Brothers, 1937.; 4 items. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - The Life of Emile Zola. Warner Brothers, 1937.; 5 items. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Lovely Lady
  - Lovely Lady., 2 items. (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Mad Genius
  - Mad Genius. Warner Brothers, 1931.; 2 items. (Box 3, Folder 11)
- The Man and the Moment
  - The Man and the Moment. Warner Brothers, 1929.; 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Midsummer Night's Dream
  - Midsummer Night's Dream. Warner Brothers, 1935.; 3 items. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Midsummer Night's Dream. Warner Brothers, 1935.; 4 items. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Midsummer Night's Dream. Warner Brothers, 1935.; 3 items. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Midsummer Night's Dream. Warner Brothers, 1935.; 4 items. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Midsummer Night's Dream. Warner Brothers, 6 items., 1935. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Midsummer Night's Dream. Warner Brothers, 1935.; 4 items. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Midsummer Night's Dream. Warner Brothers, 1935.; 4 items. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Midsummer Night's Dream. Warner Brothers, 1935.; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Midsummer Night's Dream. Warner Brothers, 1935.; 4 items. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Midsummer Night's Dream. Warner Brothers, 1935.; 4 items. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Mildred Pierce
  - Mildred Pierce. Warner Brothers, 1945.; 38 items. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Mystery of the Wax Museum
  - Mystery of the Wax Museum. Warner Brothers, 1933.; 3 items. (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Outward Bound
  - Outward Bound. Warner Brothers, 1930.; 4 items. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Outward Bound. Warner Brothers, 1930.; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 10)
- The Private Lives of Elizabeth And Essex
  - The Private Lives of Elizabeth And Essex. Warner Brothers, 1939.; 4 items. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - The Private Lives of Elizabeth And Essex. Warner Brothers, 1939.; 4 items. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - The Private Lives of Elizabeth And Essex. Warner Brothers, 1939.; 3 items. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - The Private Lives of Elizabeth And Essex. Warner Brothers, 1939.; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Road to Suez
  - Road to Suez., 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Road to Yesterday
  - Road to Yesterday. Producers Distributing Corporation, 1925.; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 16)
- The Sea Hawk
  - The Sea Hawk. Warner Brothers, 1940.; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - The Sea Hawk. Warner Brothers, 1940.; 2 items. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - The Sea Hawk. Warner Brothers, 1940.; 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - The Sea Hawk. Warner Brothers, 1940.; 4 items. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - The Sea Hawk. Warner Brothers, 1940.; 4 items. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - The Sea Hawk. Warner Brothers, 1940.; 4 items. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - The Sea Hawk. Warner Brothers, 1940.; 4 items. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - The Sea Hawk. Warner Brothers, 1940.; 2 items. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - The Sea Hawk. Warner Brothers, 1940.; 2 items. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- The Sea Wolf
  - The Sea Wolf. Warner Brothers, 1941.; 4 items. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - The Sea Wolf. Warner Brothers, 1941.; 4 items. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - The Sea Wolf. Warner Brothers, 1941.; 4 items. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - The Sea Wolf. Warner Brothers, 1941.; 4 items. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - The Sea Wolf. Warner Brothers, 1941.; 2 items. (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Silence
  - Silence., 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Song of the Flame
  - Song of the Flame. Warner Brothers, 1930.; 4 items. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Song of the Flame., 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Surrender
  - Surrender., 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Svengali. Warner Brothers, 1931.; 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Thank Your Lucky Stars. Warner Brothers, 1943. (Box 5)
  SEE Box 16.
- Thief of Paradise
  - Thief of Paradise., 3 items. (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Volga Boatman
  - Volga Boatman. Producers Distributing Corporation, 1926.; 4 items. (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Volga Boatman. Producers Distributing Corporation, 1926.; 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Yellow Lilly
  - Yellow Lilly. First National, 1928.; 3 items. (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Unidentified Material
  - 73 items. (Box 6)
  - 69 items. (Box 7)
  - 62 items. (Box 8)
  - 71 items. (Box 9)
  - 58 items. (Box 10)
  - 72 items. (Box 11)
  - 65 items. (Box 12)
  - 71 items. (Box 13)
  - Oversize framed drawings removed from Boxes 3 and 4., 1 framed storyboard from Mildred Pierce; 1 framed storyboard form The Private Lives of Elizabeth and Essex. (Box 14)
  - Oversize framed drawings removed from Boxes 3 and 4., 1 framed drawing from Midsummer Night's Dream; 1 framed drawing from the Sea Hawk. (Box 15)
  - Unidentified material., 25 items. (Box 16)
  - Unidentified material., 20 items. (Box 17)
  - Unidentified material., 20 items. (Box 18)
  - Unidentified material., 15 items. (Box 18)
  - Unidentified material., 10 items. (Box 19)
- OVERSIZE MATERIAL.
  - Dispatch from Reuter., 1 item. (Box 16)
    189
  - Doctor X., 1 item. (Box 16)
  - Don Q, Son of Zorro., 1 item. (Box 16)
  - The Great Garrick., 1 item. (Box 16)
  - Inspiration., 2 items. (Box 16)
  - Midsummer Night's Dream., 1 item. (Box 16)
  - Sea Wolf., 2 items. (Box 16)
  - Surrender., 1 item. (Box 16)
  - Thank Your Lucky Stars., 1 item. (Box 16)